嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
所以今天我们要讨论的都是错误
so today we're going to be talking all about errors
上次, 我们能够使用索引缓冲区
last time, we were able to use index buffers
并且我甚至提过你可能做错的一件事, 那将会导致出现一个错误
and I even mentioned one thing that you might do wrong, that would cause an error to appear
然而在屏幕上实际不会显示任何东西
and actually just not display anything on the screen
去看看那期吧, 如果你还没看过的话
check out that episode, if you haven't already
但今天我们会指出
but today we're gonna figure out
我们实际上可以做些什么来得到通知, 或者我们如何才能找到
what we can do to actually be notified, or how we can find out
OpenGL出了什么问题, 当我们做了错误的事情时
what has gone wrong with OpenGL, when we do something incorrectly
那可是OpenGL的很大一部分
that's a very big part of OpenGL
因为OpenGL像很多东西一样
because OpenGL like a lot of things
感觉是相当脆弱的, 我们可以很容易地打乱它
sense to be fairly fragile, and we can upset it pretty easily
那还好, 那只是开发普遍的一部分
that's okay, that's just a normal part of development
我们怎么知道我们做错了什么
how do we know what we've done wrong
以及我们如何尽快地调试并修复它
and how can we debug this as quickly as possible and fix it
这样我们就不用花一整天的时间思考
so that we don't have to spend the whole day wondering
为什么我们的屏幕是黑色的
why our screen is black
好了, 因此这儿有几种处理方法
okay, so there's a few ways to deal with this
我们不会讨论使用外部工具或类似的工具
we're not going to talk about using external tools or anything like that
我们今天会讲OpenGL实际上给我们什么
we're just going to talk today about what OpenGL actually gives us
作为一种检查错误的方法等等
as a way of checking for errors and all of that
所以基本上现在
so basically right now
我们有两种主要的方法来检查在OpenGL中的错误
we have two main ways that we can check for errors in OpenGL
其中一个叫glGetError, 它是一个我们可以调用的函数
one of them is called glGetError, it's a function we can call
它从一开始就一直在OpenGL中
it's been in OpenGL since forever since the very beginning
而它一直存在是因为
and it's conserved because of that
它兼容所有版本
it's compatible with all versions
并且它的原理很简单
and it works in a very simple way
基本上每次我们调用OpenGL函数
basically whenever we call an OpenGL function
如果发生错误
if an error were to occur
在OpenGL内存中, 有一个标志会被内部设置
a flag kind of gets set internally in OpenGL's memory
那基本上就是说发生了什么类型的错误
that basically says what type of error occurred
并且当我们调用glGetError时, 它会返回一个标志, 对吧
and when we call glGetError, that gives us back a flag, right
而通过这个标志, 我刚刚的意思是就像是一个整型
and by a flag, I just mean like an integer
总的来说这就像一个错误码
basically there's like an error code
并且如果我们实际上继续调用glGetError
and if we actually keep calling glGetError
它将会把所有标志返回给我们
it will kind of give us all the flags
因为有时候, 我们可能会产生多个错误
because sometimes, it's possible for us to generate multiple errors
如果你真的不擅长编程
if you're really bad at programming
如果你真的, 如果你做了一些很糟糕的事
if you really, if you've done something really bad
你甚至可能会导致几种不同类型的错误
you might even have caused several different types of errors
使用一个OpenGL函数调用
with a single OpenGL function call
所以因此, glGetError实际上会设置像
so because of that, glGetError will actually set like
可能有三个标志或者发生了三种不同类型的错误
maybe three flags or three different types of errors that have occurred
而当你调用glGetError
and when you call glGetError
它会给你其中一个标志, 只是一个任意的标志
it gives you one of the flags, just an arbitrary flag
所以你需要不断调用它才能得到所有的标志
so you kind of have to keep calling it to get all of them
但总的来说, 这只是我们拉取OpenGL, 问OpenGL
but basically, that's just us kind of pulling OpenGL, asking OpenGL
嘿, 一切正常吗
hey, is everything okay
我犯了什么错误吗, 现在, 那策略是正确的
have I caused any errors, now that strategy is okay
它通常是这样设置的
the way that it's typically set up is that
因为几乎所有我们调用的OpenGL函数都可能会导致错误
since pretty much any OpenGL function that we call might cause an error
让我们实际上
let's actually
首先快速看一下OpenGL中的错误是什么样子的
take a look quickly at what an error might look like in OpenGL to begin with
那么现在, 由于上一期
so right now, since the last episode
我们有这个漂亮的蓝色正方形渲染
we have this beautiful blue square rendering
现在我要做的就是关闭这个
now what I'm going to do is just close this
并且在我的glDrawElements调用中
and inside my glDrawElements call
这是我实际的DrawCall指令
which is my actual DrawCall
我要改变这个无符号整型
I'm going to change this unsigned int
在指定我们实际上有的索引数据类型时
in which specifies the type of index data that we actually have
把它改成GL_INT
to just say GL_INT
这是我最喜欢演示的错误之一
this is one of my favorite errors to demonstrate
因为它真的很简单
because it's really simple
我已经制造过很多次这样的错误
I've made this mistake plenty of times
并且它是同样有效的, 让我们按f5
and it's fellow effective, so let's hit f5
你可以看到我们得到的只是一个黑屏
you can see that all we get is well a black screen
我们的正方形我们的矩形根本就没有渲染
our square our rectangle is just not rendering at all
并且你可以在控制台上看到
and you can see that in the console
当然, 没有任何东西会被打印出来
of course, nothing gets printed at all
除了我们打印的OpenGL版本
except for our OpenGL version that we're printing
我们只得到一个黑屏
we just get a black
我们只看到黑屏, 这太糟糕了
we just get a black screen, and this absolutely sucks
我是说, 我讨厌这样
I mean, I hate this
得到一个黑屏, 并且然后必须弄清楚
getting a black screen, and then having to figure out
你实际上做错了什么, 比如你可能没有正确设置顶点数据
what you've actually done wrong, in which like maybe you haven't set up your vertex data correctly
也许你的索引缓冲区不正确, 对吧
maybe your index buffers not correct, right
也许你的着色器没运行, 就像出了什么问题
maybe your shader doesn't work, like what has gone wrong
这很难说, 当然在这种情况下
it's very hard to tell, and in this case, of course
我们只是发送GL_INT而不是GL_UNSIGNED_INT
we're just sending GL_INT instead of GL_UNSIGNED_INT
作为索引缓冲区数据类型, 所以
as the index buffer data type, so
它就会正常
it would be great
如果我们能让OpenGL告诉我们
if we could just get OpenGL to tell us
嘿, 伙计, 你的glDrawElements函数
hey man, your glDrawElements function
你在这儿传递了一个错误的整型
you're passing an incorrect int in there
你应该修复它, 那就太棒了
you should fix that right, that would be fantastic
所以我们使用glGetError的典型工作流程
so the typical kind of workflow that we have with glGetError is
首先, 比之前好很多了
first of all, pretty much before
我们给OpenGL调用的每一个函数
every function called we give to OpenGL
我们清除了所有的错误
we clear all the errors
所以我们基本上在while循环中调用glGetError
so we basically just call glGetError in like a while loop
直到它没有错误
until it equals no error
这意味着我们已经从OpenGL取回了所有可能的错误
which means that we've kind of retrieved every possible error from OpenGL
这只是我们清除所有待处理的错误的一种方法
that's just a way for us to actually clear all of the pending kind of errors
然后我们调用glDrawElements
then we call glDrawElements
并且然后我们再次调用glGetError
and then we call glGetError again
这样我们可以看到
and that way we can kind of see
是之前的glDrawElements函数吗
has this previous function called glDrawElements
这是否产生了任何类型的错误, 如果有, 是哪些错误
has that generated any kind of errors, and if so, which ones
然后我们可以把它打印到控制台或类似的地方
and then we can kind of print that to the console or something like that
为了找出哪里出了问题
to figure out what went wrong
所以那就是处理错误的一种方法
so that's one way of dealing with error
作为OpenGL最常见的方式, 最流行的方式
as an OpenGL to pretty much the most common way, the most popular way
因为它已经在规范里了
because it has been in the specification
从1.1开始, 从一开始
since 1.1, since the very beginning
并且很明显, 它和所有东西都兼容
and it's compatible obviously with pretty much everything
最近在OpenGL 4.3中, 所以它是相当新的
now recently in OpenGL 4.3, so it is quite recent
OpenGL增加了一个函数, 那基本上允许我们
OpenGL added a function that basically lets us
它叫做glDebugMessageCallback
well it's called glDebugMessageCallback
如果我们快速看一下文档
if we take a look at the documentation real quick
它被称为glDebugMessageCallback
it's called glDebugMessageCallback
你可以看到它是在OpenGL 4.3中被添加的
you can see that it's been added in OpenGL 4.3
并且它基本上就是
and basically what it is is
它允许我们指定一个指向OpenGL的函数指针
it allows us to specify a function pointer to OpenGL
OpenGL会调用我们的那个函数
an OpenGL will actually call that function of ours
当错误发生时
when an error occurs
现在这比glGetError好多了
now this is much better than glGetError
因为首先
because first of all
而不是我们不断地问OpenGL, 嘿
instead of us having to constantly ask OpenGL, hey
一切正常吗
are you all right
伙计, 一切都还好吧
man, is everything okay
当出现问题时, 它会自己告诉我们
it will tell us itself, when something goes wrong
唯一的问题是, 很明显
the only thing with this is obviously
事实上, 它在OpenGL 4.3及以上版本
the fact that it's in OpenGL 4.3 and above
所以你不能在早期版本中使用它
so you can't use that in earlier versions
但另外一个很好的方面是
but also another really good thing about this is
它实际上会给你更详细的信息
it will actually give you more detailed information
而不是只给你一个错误码
instead of just giving you an error code
这是完全没用的
which is kind of useless like completely useless
它甚至会建议一些事情, 就像它会
it will even suggest things, like it'll
用英语向你解释一下你做错了什么
explain to you what you've done wrong in English
就像令人惊奇的
like, it's amazing
这有点依赖
it's kind of dependent
当然, 是驱动之类的东西
of course, on drivers and stuff like that
但根据我的经验, 它总体上非常非常好, 比glGetError好得多
but in my experience, it generally has been very very good and much better than glGetError
今天我们完全只关注glGetError
today we're just going to be focusing on glGetError completely
它将完全是关于glGetError的
it's going to be just totally about glGetError
那种方法还是不错的
that way is still good
并且它显然与OpenGL的每个版本兼容
and it's obviously compatible with every version of OpenGL
但在以后的一期里中, 我会的
but then in a future episode, I will
我想花一整期的时间讲glDebugMessageCallback
I want to devote like a whole episode to glDebugMessageCallback
并讨论我们实际上如何使用它
and talk about how we can actually use that
因为这它更好
because it is much better
但很明显, 它并不是与OpenGL的每个版本都兼容
but obviously, it's not really compatible with every version of OpenGL
好了, 不管怎样, 让我们继续讨论glGetError
all right, anyway, let's talk more about glGetError
所以如果我翻到这里的文档
so if I flip over to the documentation here
对于glGetError, 除了告诉我们
for glGetError, apart from telling us
当然, 事实上, 它所做的是它返回的GL_NO_ERROR
of course, what it does in the fact that GL_NO_ERROR is what it returns
当我们没有错误的时候
when we don't have an error
你可以看到, GL_NO_ERROR也是零
which you can see, also that GL_NO_ERROR is guaranteed to be zero
所以那是有用的信息
so that's useful information here
它也告诉我们
it also tells us that
调用它将返回一个任意的错误标志
calling it will return an arbitrary error flag
所以不一定是所有的错误
so not necessarily all of the errors
正因为如此, 我们应该在循环中调用它来确保
and because of that we should call this in a loop to make sure that
所有错误都被重置
all of the errors are reset
并且我们得到了所有错误的信息
and we kind of get information about all of the errors
在OpenGL中发生的
that have actually occurred with OpenGL
所以那是很重要的信息
so that's kind of like important information
那是你绝对需要注意的
that you definitely need to pay attention to
我们应该在循环中调用它, 以确保我们得到所有的错误
we should be calling this inside a loop to make sure that we get all of the errors
因为如果你不那么做的话
because if you don't kind of do that
那么你可能只是通过调用glGetError来清除了一个错误
then maybe you might be clearing an error just by calling glGetError
然后你调用一个函数
then you call a function
并且然后你就会得到两个错误
and then you get two errors back
而你实际上却没有意识到
and you actually didn't realize that
哦, 实际上其中一个来自我之前调用的另一个函数
oh, actually one of them was from another function I called earlier on
因为我没有清除所有的错误
because I didn't clear all of the errors
所以你一定要看一下这个
so just make sure you kind of read this
因为关于glGetError最糟糕的事情是如果你甚至不能正确地处理那个
because the worst thing about glGetError is if you can't even do that properly
并且然后你甚至不知道发生了什么
and then you don't even know what's happening
好的, 让我们回到我们的代码中, 让我们实际上把所有这些加起来
all right, so let's put back to our code, and let's actually add all of this
所以在最上面我要做的就是创建一个函数
so what I'm going to do at the very top is make a function
并且我要在最上面做这个
and I'm actually going to do this at the very top
我要创建一个函数, static void GLClearError
I'm going to make a function, static void GLClearError
并且我把大写字母的GL写在函数的开头
and I'm kind of just writing gl and capitals here at the beginning of this function
只是让我们知道它是一个OpenGL
just to kind of let ourselves know that it is kind of an OpenGL
我们在这里写的内部函数
internal kind of function that we're writing here
并且这个函数的目的当然是为了清除所有的错误
and the purpose of this function of course is just to clear all the errors
所以我们需要做的就是像这样调用glGetError
so all we really need to do is call glGetError just like that
并且循环它, 不等于0
and while that, doesn't equal zero
而你也可以这样写, 不等于GL_NO_ERROR
so either the way you could kind of write this is does not equal GL_NO_ERROR
在那儿循环
so while there
而我们实际上从OpenGL返回一个错误
while we actually have an error back from OpenGL
让我们继续循环
let's kind of keep looping through this
所以我要在这里加一个分号, 就这样
so I'm just gonna add a semicolon here, and that's it
我们真的不需要一个函数体
we don't really need a body
我们不关心这个时间点的错误码
we don't care about error codes at this point in time
我们只是想清除所有的错误, 仅此而已
we just want to clear all the errors, that's all
现在另一种写法是
now another way you could write this
很明显, 因为我们之前看到的GL_NO_ERROR就是零
obviously because GL_NO_ERROR is guaranteed to be zero as we read earlier
你可以那样写
you could just kind of write this like that
所以当glGetError不为零时
so while glGetError is not zero
然后继续循环, 继续获取所有的错误
then keep kind of looping, keep retrieving all the errors
但我在尝试保存这些代码
but I am trying to keep this code
学习OpenGL的人会更清楚一些
a little bit more clear for people who are learning OpenGL
所以我把它写成这样
so I'm just going to write it like this
好了, 酷, 现在我们有了一种消除错误的方法
okay, cool, so we now have a way of clearing errors
让我们在这儿写另一个函数
let's write another function here
这会打印出实际发生的错误
which will actually print an error that does occur
或者函数调用后发生的所有错误
or all of the errors that do occur after a function call
所以我将这个函数设为GLCheckError或类似的东西
so I'm just going to make this void function called GLCheckError or something like that
并且这一切的目的基本上是
and all this is going to do is basically
这和另一个函数glGetError是一样的
what kind of the same thing is the other function is going to glGetError
然而, 我们并没有忽略这一点
however instead of just kind of ignoring this
我们实际上会把它赋值给其他变量
we're actually going to assign it to something
所以如你所知, glGetError返回一个GL_ENUM
so glGetError, as you know, returns a GL_ENUM
它就是一个无符号整型
which is just an unsigned int
但是, 因为这是一种和GL紧密相连的关系
but, because this is such a closely kind of tied GL full
我实际上会在这里使用GL_ENUM
I will actually use GL_ENUN here
所以while(GL_ENUM error = glGetError())
so while GL_ENUN error equals glGetError
所以我在这里给它赋值, 好吧
so I'm assigning it here, okay
所以, 我在获取错误
so, I'm kind of retrieving the error
并把它赋值给error, 这就是一行中的所有内容
and assigning it to error, kind of all in one line
很明显, 因为这是在一个自然的代码块里
obviously since this is inside a wild block
这个盲目的循环会和glGetError一直运行
this wild loop will run as long as glGetError
直到这个error变量不是0
as long as this kind of error variable is not zero
也就是它不是false
so it's not false
所以当我们有一些我们实际上获取得错误时
so while we kind of have errors that we are actually retrieving
让我们继续, 把它们打印到控制台上
let's go ahead, and just kind of print them out to the console
所以我会写std::cout
so I'm just gonna write std cout
用更好的形式输出它, 所以可能是[OpenGL Error]
kind of form out this nicely, so maybe OpenGL Error
并且然后在括号中
and then in brackets
我猜我们实际上会把错误码放在那里
I guess we'll actually put that error code
暂时就这样把
and that's it for now
好吧, 很酷, 所以现在我们有一个非常简单的方法
allright, pretty cool, so now we have a very very simple way of
实际检查我们是否有错误
actually checking to see if we have an error
那么, 让我们来测试一下, 我要到这里来
so, let's just test this out, so I'm going to go down here
来到我们绘制函数
to my draw function
现在我会在这里制造一个错误, 对吧
now I have made a mistake here, right
你可以看到我正在使用GL_INT而不是GL_UNSIGNED_INT
you can see I'm using GL_INT and not GL_UNSIGNED_INT
我仍然会得到那个错误码整数
I've still got that code int
首先我要做得就是调用GLClearError
the first thing I'm going to do is call GLClearError
对吧, 为了清除我们所有的错误
right, to clear all of our errors
然后在这个函数之后调用GLCheckError
and then finally GLCheckError after the function
所以你可以看到这个的原理
so you can kind of see how this works
我们首先清除所有错误
we clear all the errors first
为了确保我们不会从其他函数得到其他任何错误
to make sure that we don't have any other errors from other functions
然后调用我们实际的函数
we then call our actual function
而然后就是检查错误, 通过那样的方式, 我们可以确保
and then we check errors, that way we can kind of make sure
所有的错误实际上都是来自这个函数
that all of the errors are actually coming from this function
我们刚刚从上次函数调用中得到错误
and we're just getting the errors from our last function call
好了, 所以现在让我们按f5, 看看会发生什么
allright, so now let's just hit f5 and see what happens
好了, 看看这个, 看看这个
okay, look at this, check this out
所以在我们的渲染循环中, 我们实际上得到了
so in our rendering loop, we're actually getting
当我把马上它拉一下
if I just pulls this for a sec
我们实际上得到了占位的OpenGL Error, 然后是1280, 太棒了
we're actually getting OpenGL Error appropriating and then 1280, fantastic
所以我们知道我们已经做了一些错事
so we know that we've done something wrong
而当我们返回我们的文档
and if we go back to our documentation
你可以看到下面这些错误, 我们实际上不得不去找
you can see the following errors, that we actually have to find
现在其中哪个是1280, 是真正的问题
now which one of these is 1280 is the real question
为了找出那个, 让我们继续
to figure that out, let's go ahead and
实际上来到我们的OpenGL头文件
actually go to our OpenGL header file
所以这个会在glew.h里面
so this will be in glew for us
当我们输入1280, 我们实际上没有得到任何东西
if we type in 1280, we're not actually going to get anything
因为OpenGL用十六进制表示法定义了它的所有错误码
because OpenGL defines all of its in in hexadecimal notation
所以我们实际上要做的是将错误代码从十进制转换成十六进制
so what we'll actually have to do is convert that error code from decimal into hex
要做到这一点, 我只需要在这个错误函数中设置一个断点
to do that, I'm just going to set a breakpoint into this error function here
我要选择这个, 就这样, 重新运行我的程序
I'm going to select this, so that's it, resumes my program
你可以看到我们得到了1280, 当我右键点击这里
you can see we have 1280, if I just right click here
我可以用十六进制显示
I can go hexadecimal display
你可以看到错误码是十六进制的500
and you can see the error code is just 500 here in hex
所以当我返回到我的glew头文件时
so if I go back to my glew header file
然后搜索500, 可能开头有0x0
and search for 500, maybe a zero x zero at the beginning
你可以看到那个了
you can see that
这里有我们所有的无效错误, 对吧
here we have all of our invalid kind of errors, right
我们所有的错误码
all of our error codes
所以500意味着无效的枚举
so if 500 means invalid enum
现在, 在这个方面
now, at this point
对我们来说, 编写一个函数是非常明智的
it would be very wise for us to actually write a function
它将这些数字转换成实际的单词
which translates these numbers into actual words
所以基本上, 如果我们的错误代码是GL_INVALID_ENUM
so basically, if our error code is GL_INVALID_ENUM
就像这里一样
as it is here
也许将invalid enum打印到实际屏幕上, 那就好了
maybe print invalid enum to the actual screen, that would be nice
但我不会在这里那么做, 只是不想浪费时间
but I'm not going to do that here, just not to waste time
所以你可以看到我们的错误代码在这里是无效的枚举
so you can see that our error code here is invalid enum
这告诉我们, 实际上
which tells us that we've actually
把无效值传递到了OpenGL函数中
passed in an invalid value into an OpenGL function
特别是一个无效的枚举
and specifically an invalid enum
现在, 在这个例子中, 那当然是有道理的
now, in this case, that of course makes sense
因为GL_INT是我们实际传递的无效枚举
because GL_INT is the actual invalid enum we've passed
它应该是无符号整型
it should be unsigned int
你可以看到虽然这里
you can see though there
我们在这里和这里所做的有一些缺陷
there are a few flaws with what we've done here and
它真的不是
it's not really
它不是缺陷, 只是没有那么好
it's not that it's flawed it's just it's not that great
对吧, 我的意思是我们知道我们犯了一个错误
right, I mean we know we're getting an error
我们知道, 我们可以使用它, 它在渲染循环中
we know it, we can kind of did use that, it is inside the render loop
而它不是在OpenGL的所有类型中
but it's not in all the kind of OpenGL
初始化代码或类似于我们所做的任何事情
initialization code or anything like that that we did
比如创建顶点或索引缓冲区
such as creating our vertex or index buffer
因为我们基本上每一帧就会得到错误
because we're getting errors like every frame basically
所以我们知道这里有些东西, 对吧
so we know is something here, right
实际上我们不知道的是它发生在哪一行代码上
what we don't know is actually which line of code it occurred on
所以那是一个问题, 并且不仅如此
so that's kind of an issue, and not only that
但是你也可以看到这个有点
but you can see the code is a little bit
笨重, 我的意识是如果我们返回这儿
clunky, I mean if we have to go back up here
基本上就是调用清除错误, 然后在每个函数之前检查错误, 就像
and basically call clear error and check error before every function, like
清除错误而后检查
clear error and then check error
那只是在我们的代码取出来
that's going to just pull out our code
并且让扩展变得更加困难, 比如我们想要什么
and make it so much harder to breed, like where would we want any of that
那只会给我们带来错误检查的负担
that's going to just burden us with error checking
这是我们应该一直自动地这样做, 对吧
which we should be doing just automatically all the time, right
所以这里有一些方法来解决这个
so there are a few ways of dealing with this
对于我们的第一个问题
for our first problem
我们很高兴知道
it'd be nice for us to know
实际发生这个错误的代码行
the line of code on which this error actually occurred on
现在我们可以自己手动完成
now we can kind of do that manually ourselves
如果我们在这里重新运行我们的程序
if we kind of resume our program here
所以它正在运行
so it is running
它仍然在向控制台发送错误
it is still kind of spamming all of this to the console
我确实在这个GLCheckError函数中放置了一个断点来找到
I did place a breakpoint here in this GLCheckError function to figure out
这个值的十六进制值
what kind of value this was in hex
你可以看到当我看到调用堆栈
you can see if I look at the call stack
双击这里
and I double click over here
我知道它发生在这行上
I know that it's happened on this line
就是glDrawElements
which is glDrawElements
所以我确实知道发生在哪行代码上了
so I do kind of know what line of code had happened on
然而, 这涉及到我放置一个断点和所有这些
however that involves me placing a breakpoint and all of that
这不太有趣
it's not too fun
在这个例子中, 不管如何, 我们也知道它发生在哪一行
and also in this case, we kind of know what line it happened on anyway
因为我们只检查一个函数的错误
because we're only checking one function for errors
但我们实际上可以做的就是得到实际的调试器
but what we can actually do is get our actual debugger
暂停执行并在导致错误的代码行上中断
to just pause execution and break on the line that causes that error
对吧, 我们可以通过使用断言来实现这一点
right, and we can do that by just using an assert
基本上, 一个断言就是
basically an assertion is
当你断言某事是true是false时
when you assert if something is true or false
并且如果那个条件是false的
and if that kind of condition is false
你通常要么将消息写入控制台
you typically like either write a message to the console
要么只是停止程序的执行
or just kind of stop execution of the program
并且在那行中断
and kind of break on that line
所以它有点像设置一个断点
so it's kind of like placing a breakpoint
但我们实际上可以通过代码放置断点
but we can actually place a breakpoint through code
对吧, 我们实际上可以告诉我们的调试器
right, we can actually tell our kind of debugger
嘿, 当你运行到这儿这行代码时
hey, if you run into this line of code here
进入到我调用的这个函数, 在这儿中断而不是断点
into this function that I'm calling, break instead of breakpoint here
只是中断, 对吧, 它比较酷
and just break, right, it's pretty cool
我们一定要在c++系列教程中讲更多关于断言的东西
we're definitely going to talk more about assertions in the c++ series
一旦视频制作完成, 我会有一个链接在那里
I'll have a link up there once that video is made
但是让我们来看看, 我们是如何做到这一点的。
but let's take a look at how we can actually do that
所以为了实现那个, 我会
so to do that, I'm just going to
重写一点点这个检查错误的函数
kind of rewrite this check error function a little bit
首先是让它返回一个布尔
I'm going to first of all get it to return a boolean
让我们也停止执行那个程序
let's just stop execution of that program as well
并且叫它GLLogCall, 明白吧
and I'll call this GLLogCall, okay
因为我们马上将为它添加更多功能
because we'll add some more features to it in a minute
现在当这个确实返回一个错误
now if this does return an error
事实上, 一旦发生这种情况
and in fact as soon as it does
现在我会在这儿返回false
I'm just going to call return false here now
现在你可能会质疑这个循环的有效性
you might kind of question the validity of this loop now
为什么这个一定要在一个while循环中
why does this have to be in a while loop
如果你从第一次迭代返回的话
if you're returning from the first iteration
但这只是从现在开始的一种展示
but this is just kind of to demonstrate from now
所以我真的不在意
so I don't really care
然后返回true
and then return true
基本上, 如果你的返回值为false
so basically if where your return false from this
这意味着我们的gl调用没有成功
it means that our gl call was not successful
然后到这里来
I'm then going to come up here
而我实际上要写一个宏
and I'm actually going to write a macro
就是我们的断言, 对吧, 所以#define ASSERT(x)
which is our assertion, right, so define ASSERT x
所有这些都是验证一个条件
so all this is going to do is validate a condition
所以我们不得不就像这样写它
so we'll have to write it like this
如果你这样写的话, 它确实不会运行
if you kind of write it like this, it won't really work
因为一些原因
because of reasons
我们会有一期关于c++宏的视频
we'll have a video about c++ macros and all that
等制作好了, 我会把它链接放这儿的
again, I'll link it up there when that's actually made
但是我们必须像这样把条件用括号括起来
but we have to write our condition wrapped in parentheses like this
并且如果这是false
and if this was false
我要调用一个函数
I'm just going to call a function
基本上就是会在代码中插入一个断点然后中断调试器
which will basically insert a breakpoint at that moment in code and just break the debugger
所以这是编译器的固有特性
so this is an intrinsic to your compiler
这基本上意味着
which basically means that
你在这里调用的函数将与你正在使用的编译器不同
this function that you call here is going to be different forage compiler that you're using
当我在c++系列中讲到断言时
when I cover assertions in the c++ series
我将展示这个函数的用途, 比如所有的编译和其他
I will show what the function is for like all compiles and all of that
无论如何, 我相信你可以用谷歌搜索它
I'm sure you can google it, anyway
但因为我们这儿正在用VS
but because we're using visual studio here and
这也不是关于c++, 而是关于OpenGL
this isn't really about c++, about OpenGL
我会用MSVC(微软的VC库)函数
I'm just going to use the MSVC function
就是像那样的__debugbreak
which is underscore undiscovered debugbreak like that
__让我们知道它是一个编译器本身的
the underscore underscore kind of lets us know that it's a compiler intrinsic
这意味着它是MSVC特有的
which means that it's specific to MSVC
而它在clang、gcc或其他任何编译器中都不起作用
and it won't work in clang or gcc, or any of those compilers
好了, 酷, 这是我们的断言函数
okay, so that's pretty cool, that's our assertion function
所以我现在能做的就是
so what I can do now
基本上就是我们的GLLogCall, 放在下面这儿
is basically where we have this GLLogCall over here at the bottom
并且这个GLCheckError实际上应该改成GLLogCall
and this GLCheckError will actually it's called GLLogCall
现在让我们就像那样把它重命名为GLLogCall
now let's just rename it to GLLogCall like that
我可以断言那个
I can assert that
所以我会写ASSERT, 并且我会把它用括号括起来
so I'll write ASSERT, and I'll wrap this in parenthesis like that
然后按f5来运行我的程序
and I'll hit f5 to run my program
所以如果这个返回false, 它应该中断调试器
so if this returns false, it should just break the debug
而你可以看到, 看看那个
and you can see, look at that
OpenGL.exe在这一行上触发了一个断点
OpenGL.exe triggered a breakpoint on this exact line
我们现在确切地知道我们的程序不会继续运行并且
we know exactly now our program does not continue running and
不会一直将错误发送到我们的控制台
doesn't keep spamming the error into our console
我们的控制台只读取到了OpenGL Error(1280)
our console just reads OpenGL Error 1280
而我们就可以那个错误发生在哪儿了
and we can see where that error occurred
那有多酷啊
how cool is that much better
但我们可以做得更好
but we can do a lot better than this
实际上下一步要做的就是
the next step is actually going to be just to
去掉清除错误的调用
get rid of having to call clear error
以及在每个函数后面的GLLogCall调用
and then log call after every function
让我们创建一种宏来为我们做到这一点
let's invent some kind of macro that does that for us
所以当我们来到顶部, 我们定义所有宏的地方
so if we go up to the top, where we define all of our macros
我会定义另一个叫GLCall的宏, 对吧
I'm going to define another one called GLCall, right
x将是我们调用的函数
x is going to be the function essentially that we're calling
并且在这儿, 实际上我首先要做的就是
and over here, the first thing that I'm actually going to do
调用GLClearError以确保我们已清除所有内容
is call GLClearError to make sure that we clear everything
现在, 我不想把这个所有代码写在一行上
now, I don't want to write all this code on one line
因为它看起来看困难
because it'll be hard to read
所以我要添加一个反斜杠, 然后回车
so I'm just going to add a backslash and then hit enter
这个基本上会忽视这个新的换行符
this basically ignores the new line character
这样我们就可以在另一行继续写这个宏了
so that we can continue writing this macro on another line
然后我就写x;
I'm then going to just write x semicolon
它基本上会插入我们指定的函数, 所以我们调用它
which basically will insert that function we've specified, so that we call it
并且然后再加个反斜杠
and again another backslash
现在我还要提到的一件事是确保
now one more thing I have to mention is make sure
当你添加反斜杠时, 你需要插入一个空格
when you put the backslash, you'd only insert a space
然后再输入你的其他代码
and then enter otherwise yours
你在这儿仍会有个换行符
you still got the new line character there
如果你添加反斜杠后面没有空格然后就回车的话
you have to put a backslash and then with no spaces, press enter
最后, 我就调用GLLogCall
and then finally I'm just going to call GLLogCall
但这次实际上在一个断言中
but this time actually inside an assertion
像那样输入这个GLLogCall
so like this GLLogCall like that
我不会在这里放分号之类的东西
and I'm not going to put like a semicolon or anything over here
因为我们不需要
because we don't need to
因为在我们调用GLCall
because after we call GLCall
我们就是以分号结束的
we'll end it with a semicolon
好了, 所以现在, 让我们滚动到我们代码这里
all right so now let's scroll down to our code here
并且替换调用GLClearError, 然后断言GLLogCall
and instead of having to call GLClearError and then asserting that GLLogCall
实际上我们能做的就是
what we can actually do is
就这样用一个GLCall来包裹这个gldrawerelements
just wrap this glDrawElements with a GLCall just like that
太酷了, 现在我们就可以按f5了
how cool is that, and now we can hit f5
好了, 并且在这儿我们得到了同样的结果
all right, and we get the same result here
但是你现在可以看到它更清楚了
but you can see now it's even more clear
它实际上就在这个glDrawElements这行上
it's actually on this glDrawElements line
所以我们知道到底出了什么问题, 现在
so we know exactly what's gone wrong, now now
我们实际上可以做的另一件事是这个错误消息
one more thing we can actually do is this error message
没有指定发生实际错误的文件或行
doesn't specify which file or line the actual error occurred on
我们真的不太需要那个
we don't really need that
因为我们是通过调试器运行的
because we're running through the debugger
它只是一个断点, 对吧
and it just breakpoints, right
我们很容易看到在哪个文件的哪行
and it's easy for us to see what file in line
但是如果我们在没有调试器之类的情况下运行它
but if we're running it without the debugger or anything like that
对于控制台来说, 它还是不错的
it would still be nice for the console
以某种方式打印文件和代码行
right to somehow print out the file and line of code
这个实际错误发生的地方, 甚至可能是函数名
this actual error happened on, maybe even the function name
所以让我们看看我们是否能实现那个
so let's see if we can do that
让我们回到这儿
let's go back out of here
而我实际上要做的就是
and what I'm actually going to do
让这个GLLogCall接收更多的参数
is make this GLLogCall accept some more parameters
所以我们添加const char* function
so we'll add const char function
这是函数的名称
which will be the name of the function
我们尝试调用它的所有参数等等
we tried to call with all of its arguments and everything
然后添加const char* file, 这是c++源文件
we'll add const char* file, which will be the c++ source file
这个函数实际调用的文件
where this function was actually called from
最后是int line
and then finally int line
所以我要对这个错误做的就是添加所有这些细节
so what I'll do to this error is I'll add all of those details
所以当我们打印错误消息时候
so when we print our error message
我也会把这个函数加进去
I'll also add in the function which will be just function
实际上我会把它换行, 这样你们就可以看到
I'll actually move this down here, so you guys can see
在那个函数后面我们添加了一个空格
we'll add a space after that function
然后就是文件
then we'll add file
然后像那样一个冒号, 然后才是代码行
then maybe a colon like that and then the line of code
好了, 太棒了
okay, great
所以现在我们需要填充所有的信息
so now we need to fill all of that information in
所以在这个GLLogCall中
so inside this GLLogCall
实际上可以用宏指出
we can actually use macros to figure out
我们调用这个函数的文件或行
which file or line we call this function from
然而不仅如此
and not only that
而我们也可以
but we can also
当我们实际上传入这个函数时
since we are actually passing in this function
实际上我们可以把x转成一个字符串
we can actually turn in whatever x is into a string
而那就是我们如何打印我们的函数名称
and that's how we'll print our function name
所以为了实现那个
and so to do that
我会在x前面加上#, 这会把它转成一个字符串
I'm just going to write hash in front of x, which turns it into a string
然后就是这个文件, 它是__FILE__
and then for the file, it's underscore underscore file in all caps
不像调试器中断, 这不是一个特性
now unlike the debug break, this is not an intrinsic
它应该被所有编译器支持的
it should be supported by all compilers
所以不用担心那个
so don't worry about that
最后这个代码行, 它也是像那样的__LINE__, 好了
and then finally for the line, again it's just underscore underscore line like that, okay
很酷的东西
pretty cool stuff
让我们再次尝试运行我们的代码
let's try and run our code again
现在当这里中断后, 当我们回到我们的控制台
now when this breaks, if we go back to our console
看看这个, 我们看到了glDrawElements
check this out, we see glDrawElements
以及我们实际的参数, GL_TRIANGLES, 6, GL_INT, nullptr
with our actual parameters, GL_TRIANGLES, six, GL_INT, nullptr
并且然后我们实际上也看到了这个Application.cpp源文件的全路径
and then we actually have a full path to this Application.cpp source file
接下来就是实际的代码行166
followed by the actual line of code one sixty six
你可以看到的是断点所在的代码行
which you can see is line of code that their breakpoint is on
那个太酷了
how cool is that
所以我们现在知道到底出了什么问题
so we now know exactly what's gone wrong
在哪儿发生的, 我们实际上做了什么, 就像
where and what we've actually, like what
我们实际上尝试调用什么代码失败了
what code we actually tried to call that failed
因为我们已经在控制台打印了它的一切
because we're printing it all to the console
很酷的东西, 现在有点多
pretty cool stuff, now a lot
我们这个接收的有点多
now I know this is a lot to take in
如果你不熟悉c++宏的话
if you're not familiar with c++ macros
这就是当那个视频准备好了
which is why that video when it's ready
我们会把链接放那儿等等
we'll be linked up there and all of that
而我应该很快就会制作那期
and I should do that probably very soon
但是你可以看到, 在c++和宏的加成下
but you can see, with the power of c++ and macros
我们可以真的可以改进OpenGL调试
we can like really improve this OpenGL debugging
特别是这里最有用的功能
and specifically the most useful feature here
说实话, 实际上就是那个调试器中断
to be honest is that actual debug break
能够在实际代码行上中断
just being able to break on that actual line
通过我们创建的那个断言
by that assetion that we've kind of created
真的真的很有用
is really really useful
因为它能让我们确切地知道我们现在哪里出了问题
because it kind of lets us know exactly where we've gone wrong now
你现在通过这个GLCall应该能做的很多
what you should do now with this GLCall is actually pretty much
我们调用的每一个OpenGL函数
every OpenGL function we ever call
像glGen所有东西
like glGen just everything
我们应该用GLCall把那个包装起来
we should be wrapping that with GLCall
所以基本上我在这里要做的就是很快地做到这一点
so basically what I'm going to do here is just do that really quickly
每个独立的OpenGL函数调用都被包含在GLCall中
every single OpenGL function call surrounded in GLCall
因为我用一种非常简单的方式写了这个宏
now because I wrote this macro in a very simple kind of way
这儿会有些缺陷
there are a few flaws
例如, 如果我们使用一行if语句
for example, if we use a one-line if statement
这个就不会运行
this isn't going to work
因为只有第一行会在if语句内
because just the first line is going to be inside the if statement
这些都不是true
and these true won't be in all of that
你可以通过包围这个范围来解决此问题
you can fix that by just surrounded this here scope
就像一个do-while(0)循环, 然后再做一遍
and like a do while zero loop and all of that again
我在那期关于宏的视频中讲过那个
I talked about that in the macros video
所以这个函数
so kind of so kind of take this function
我在这儿写的这个代码就是
this code that I've written here is
一种实现这个的真的很基础很简单的方法
just a really kind of basic simple way of doing this
同时, 把它放在一个范围内也不是很好
also putting it in a scope isn't very preferable
因为如果你真的有赋值操作的话
because if you actually have values being assigned
就像如果, 你需要我们在这儿写的这个着色器源码
like if, you have the shader code that we wrote over here
你可以看到调用glCreateProgram的程序实际赋值给了它
you can see the calling glCreateProgram actually assigns it
而我们仍然可以在GLCall内部实现那个
so we can still do that inside GLCall
只是确保你要这样做
just make sure you do it like this
然而问题是如果我们将其包装在一个范围内
however the issue is that if we were to wrap that in a scope
那么program这个变量将超出这里的范围
program would be out of scope over here
所以如果我们像那样放一个大括号
so if we were to kind of put curly brackets like that
围绕这个为了保持它在一个范围
around this to keep it all in one scope
然后我们有一个问题, 就是不能真正使用这里的program
then we have the issue of not really being able to use program over here
因为这就像我们把program包装在一个源码中一样
because it's like if we wrapped program in a source code kind of like that
它无法被访问了
it wouldn't be accessible anymore
正如你在这儿看到的
as you can see here
因此, 你必须意识到一些阻碍
so there are a few kind of setbacks that you have to be aware of
以及所有那些, 我会继续的
and all that, I'm going to go ahead
并且把剩下所有的这些函数添加上GLCall
and add GLCall to the rest of all these functions
那个源码在patreon上有提供
that source code is available for patreon
如果你通过patreon.com/TheCherno支持这个系列
if you support the series by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
你基本上会收到每一期的源代码
you will receive basically the source code to every single episode
那种一期接一期的
kind of episode by episode
并且那会有我写的所有描述
and that will have all the story written
当然我会做那个
of course I'll do that
我只是不想浪费你们的时间
I'm not gonna waste your time
并且你只要知道把GLCall加到你面前的每一个函数
and just you know write GLCall add every single function in front of you
因为你已经get到了那个点
because you kind of get the point
但不管如何, 那只是基础的OpenGL错误检测, 对吧
but anyway, that is basically OpenGL error checking, right
那就是我喜欢如何实现它的
that's how I like to do it
我喜欢每个独立函数调用包装起来
I like to just wrap every single function call
每个独立的OpenGL函数调用
every single OpenGL function call
在GLCall中
inside GLCall and
基本上就是只要我有一个错误, 那就会触发断点
basically that will just breakpoint whenever I have an error
关于glDebugMessageCallback, 我们会在后面的一期中讨论
glDebugMessageCallback, we will talk about in a later episode
因为那个也真的很有用
because that is also very useful
从理论上讲, 意味着我们不必做所有这些
and kind of theoretically means we don't have to do all of this
虽然我发现我仍然喜欢这样做
although I find I still like doing this
因为你确实得到了与OpenGL早期版本的兼容性
because you do get the compatibility with earlier versions of OpenGL
而且这种方法也没有什么问题
and also there's nothing really wrong with this method
只是glDebugMessageCallback确实会给你提供更多信息
it's just the glDebugMessageCallback does give you more information
在所有这些方面都稍微有用一点
and is slightly more useful in all of that
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed the video
如果你喜欢的话, 就点击那个点赞按钮
if you did, you hit that like button
正如我之前提到的
as I mentioned earlier
你可以通过patreon.com/TheCherno来支持这个系列
you can support this series by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
得到一些很酷的奖励
and get some pretty cool rewards
最后我们也有一个discord服务
finally we also have a discord server
你可以讨论这期内容等等
where you can discuss this episode and all of that
thecherno.com/discord是你在那里得到邀请的方式
thecherno.com/discord is how you get an invite there
这是一个非常酷的社区, 你可以在这里谈论
it's a really cool community where you can actually talk about
你在这一期看到的一切
everything you've seen in this episode
让我知道你对OpenGL错误检查的看法
let me know what you think about OpenGL error checking
或者如果你有一个非常酷的方法来检查错误
or maybe if you have a really cool way of actually checking errors
那可不像我的方法那么酷
that isn't as cool as my way
那么一定要在下面留言
then definitely leave a comment below
或者只是在一般情况下你是怎么调试OpenGL的
or just in general what you do to debug OpenGL
因为我知道那是个大问题
because I know that it can be a huge issue and
这就是为什么我不
that's why I'm not
这就是为什么我不太热衷于OpenGL的原因之一
that's one of the reasons why I'm not the biggest fan of OpenGL
不论如何, 下次再见, 拜
anyway, I'll see you guys in the next video, goodbye